A Guide to the Papers of Ernest Hemingway, 1925-1961, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Correspondence
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1951 February 7, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:59)
    Big work almost finished, which can be broken into three big publishable books. Hotchner's television deal sounds good, but Hemingway doesn't want to stop writing for a New York appearance. Mary, Adriana, and her mother left for a trip. Wants to finish book so he can shoot in the International Championships. Scandal in Paris and Venice that Adriana is the girl in "that book we all wrote. You know this is impossible." Tells Hotchner what Sam Langford said: "that you could sweat out eating too much and you could sweat out beer and whiskey but nobody could sweat out women." Discusses sights Adriana should see in New York. 6250-x
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1951 [March 26] "Easter Sunday", TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:60)
    Apologizes for everyone being sick. Wants Hotchner to sell stories without Hemingway's having to talk or make appearances. His play [The Fifth Column] subversive now, but not when he wrote it. Hemingway doesn't want to be a T.V. personality. He should be writing a novel. Hemingway worrying a lot. His writing kills the worry: "So I work until I'm dead and that kills the worry and me too." Then he worries about the scandal he may have caused in Venice. "Hell if we could only make some money and me not have to photograph or talk." A person like Don Ameche who has "poise, clarity, naturalness, and charm" can deal with this strain. 6250-x
  - Ernest Hemingway to Miss Cohen, 1952 July 20, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:60A)
    Discusses in detail the Caedmon Publishers' proposal to do a recording of him reading his works. Accompanying the letter are carbon copies of three letters from Barbara Cohen to Hemingway proposing the project, discussing various aspects of it, and offering him a $500 advance plus a 10% royalty. There is also a carbon of a brief note from Cohen to Alfred Rice sending a copy of her first letter to Hemingway with the comment "Hope springs eternal." 6250-z
  - E. Hemignstein alias Mr. Papa [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch-Maru" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1952 July 21, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:61)
    Thanks him for finding opening for Mary to write piece. Hemingway turns 53 and tells Hotchner how much he appreciates his friendship. Hemingway in financial difficulties, but possibilities for money. He will be in the clear if it sells. Makes changes to The Snows of Kilimanjaro. Discusses their mutual friends and upcoming boxing matches with Marciano and Mathews. 6250-x
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Ed [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1952 August 4, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:62)
    Sorry about Mark, who died. Hemingway knew him during the war and he took the "same way out" as Scott, which "seems to be an Irish ending." Wishes he knew Mark better because he was "an awful good guy." Wishes he was racing again with Hotchner. Talks about a bar-fight Hemingway was in: "I nailed him with two left hooks and a right chop." 6250-f
  - Ernest and Mary Hemingway to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1953 July 24, APC, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:63)
    He is watching a horse race and missing Hotchner. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Peter [Viertel], 1954 January 21, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:63A)
    Hemingway writes from Nairobi mentioning possibly seeking employment as temporary game ranger, surveying elephants and fish, and flying with Roy Marsch; and apologizes for not writing Jigee Viertel. Writes in detail about looking "after a leopard who killed 10 goats in one night..."; boxing with native "boys"; and learning to hunt with a spear, giving a list of animals killed to date. Also refers to a [movie collaboration?] with Faulkner and Hughes, noting "all the stories I know now are barrred from the screen on acct. of miscegenation. Also all to rough." 6250-v
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotchmanship" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1954 June 21, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:64)
    Writing from on board the Morosen. Talks of John Houston and Paul Kohner. Al had not deposited book money, which caused over-drafts covered by Scribner's. Tells of bullfights and of Cordoba who tossed on his head by a bull. Saw the Pyrenees. Thinks he will beat "this rap" if kidneys straighten out. Cutting down on drinking. Liked Cardiz very much. 6250-f
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Burt?] MacBride, 1954 June 29, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:64A)
    Hemingway is working on a "long thing" and "would not be able to get to stories for a while." He is also committed to pieces for Esquire but hopes will have something for him in the future. In top left corner margin is written "HPB + pls return for file BM." In top right corner margin is written "BM can't we get a 1st look? Important B" 6250-aa
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Peter [Viertel], 1954 August 21, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:64B)
    Discusses an upcoming fishing trip; writing progress; and the "comic aspects" of screen adaptations, particularly in reference to Gregory Peck in The purple plain. He sends thanks for moccasins and mentions a postal strike and other interferences in his life including people "louseing up the time should be re-charging the batteries ...." Mentions Hans F. Koenekamp, Don Page, George Brown who is coming down to get him in shape, and Bob Parrish. 6250-ac
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to Mrs. L. Figgis, 1954 September 24, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:64C)
    Written in the aftermath of his near fatal plane crash while on safari in Uganda, Hemingway discusses the preservation of his "trophies" by Zimmerman, disparages Robert Ruark's African safari article, enquires about her children and their business, promises to send a check for deposit in Mary Hemingway's account, and thanks her for news about mutual acquaintances. 6250-ad
  - Hemingstein of Harrow [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1955 June [20], TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:65)
    Talks about problems with children and Hemingway's home in Key West. Would be nice if Hotchner came down to visit him. Frustrated with Marlene. "[B]oth you and I put in a hell of a lot of time being God's Little Gentlemen to people who would regard cutting off our balls as merely a regrettable incident." They will have fun when he comes down. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] and M[ary Hemingway] to [Mr. and Mrs. Hotchner], [1955 December 15], Christmas Card with envelope, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:66)
    "Sorry not written, been laid up." 6250-f
  - Local Hemingstein of Tel Aviv [Ernest Hemingway] to "Querido Hotchmaru" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1956 September 14, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:67)
    News of their travels to Escorial for one month and their new address in Paris. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotchmanship" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1956 September 30, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:68)
    Discusses his trip to Madrid, about bullfighter friends and the bullfighting experiences. Asks for Hotchner's help for Alistair MacIntosh, a friend of Hemingway's writing a book. Hemingway wrote six short stories. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotchenroll" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1957 May 28, TLS with autograph postscript, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:69)
    Discusses his business dealings with Alfred [Rice] and split in fees between all of them. Talks about the sales of Battler. Hemingway states that he is "not really a very big shit about monies; or maybe [he] is and nobody told [him]." Difficulties of not having hard liquor: "It is about as much fun as driving a racing motor car without lubrication for a while." Sorry that Hotchner has so much work on C.B.S. thing. Both Hemingway and Mary are in good health. Writing Peter Buckley about his bull book: "God save us from amateurs. They kill you." 6250-f
  - Hemingstein [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1957 August 8, TLS with autograph corrections, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:70)
    Discusses Alfred [Rice] and business problems with him. Half-way through sixth month of doing without liquor. Liver improved but not cured. Tells of health worries. Problems with Mary's mother who is bothering Mary all the time, and Bunby's "extravagant wife problems." Gigi in hospital. Has lots of worries. Easier when he could drink and cheer up. Mary would rather have Hotchner around than anyone else.
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotchnick" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1957 December 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:71)
    Talks about his health, children, and tax problems caused by Alfred [Rice], his tax lawyer. Alfred did some illegal things using Hemingway's money. Had warned Alfred to pay up. Hemingway never cut corners, but now he owes a lot. Alfred tells him to get to work, and Hemingway has written 750-1,200 words a day since November 5. Will fight his way out of this one as our of every other one. 6250-f
  - Mary Papa [Mary and Ernest Hemingway] to [Edward] Hotchner, 1958 May 6, telegram, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:72)
    Congratulates Alfred on his performance. Read Crosby review and happiest that Alfred is getting deserved recognition. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], [1958] August 26, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:73)
    Hadn't written on account of book. Against Naples story being transplanted to Venice where gangsters don't come from: "They would not permit this and I didn't think it chic repayment of their many kindnesses to us." Upset about Town and Country pieces; errors should have been caught. Alfred [Rice] told to split with Hotchner on whatever he considered right. Hemingway knows he can believe nothing he says. Asks Hotchner if the deal was fouled up. Includes photocopy TLS Mary Hemingway to Hotchner, 1958 August 26. See Mary Hemingway correspondence for original. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], [1958 November 5], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:74)
    Don't let year go by without them getting together. Classy shooting. Fine country and people. Next best thing to Spain and very like it. Verso: Mary Hemingway to Hotch, 1958 November 5. 6250-f
  - Ernest Hemingway to [Bronislaw] Zielinski, 1958 November 5, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope (Box-folder 3:75)
    Gives specific details on traveling to Idaho. 6250-g
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Bron" [Bronislaw Zielinski], 1958 November 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:76)
    Great fun having him visit and he left many friends. Sorry about the bad luck on the trip. After he left it snowed heavily and they had some good duck hunting. Discusses [The Green Hills of Africa] royalties. Enjoy his time while in the United States and give his best to Polish writers when he gets home. 6250-g
  - Mr. Papa [Ernest Hemingway] to "Bron" [Bronislaw Zielinski], 1959 February 15, LS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:77)
    Sorry not to have written Zielinski since Malaga. Hemingway has had trouble and has been working very hard. Mary fractured her arm very badly which required drastic surgery. Took much of Hemingway's time. Valerie has helped out a lot but Hemingway is over-worked trying to make up for lost time. They all toasted Zielinski at Christmas and New Year's. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary, Valerie [Danby-Smith]. 6250-g
  - [Ernest] Hemingway to [Frank Stanton], [1959 March], ANS, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:78)
    "Artist without talent stop portrait without merit stop hope show will be better stop Very Best luck and thanks." Draft for telegram message written on back of envelope. 6250-f
  - Ernest [Hemingway] to "Bron" [Bronislaw Zielinski], 1959 April 12, ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:79)
    Thanks for his fine letters, the pictures, and the clippings. Hemingway has been working very hard. Wanted to write him but kept on writing and hunting. Good shooting after he left. After duck season they hunted jack-rabbits for the farmers and trapped magpies. Details their stops on the way to Key West. Relates how in Texas "every filling station for three hundred miles had been robbed in one night." Talks about his loss of weight, exercise routine, the revolution in Cuba. Cannot trust [Alfred] Rice. Expects to be in Spain in May. 6250-g
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to [Edward] Hotchner, 1959 June 18, D, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:80)
    Telegram. If Hotchner cannot make Madrid on 26th come directly to Suecia and they will drive to Zaragoza for Antonio [Ordez]'s reappearance. Will have everything set for Pamplona, Valencia, etc. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 June 18, 2 pp. on 2 l. with carbon copy and envelope. (Box-folder 3:81)
    Antonio [Ordez] fights in Zaragoza 27th. If he can get to Madrid by 26th, wonderful. Details plans for the following days. Antonio going with them because he is not fighting, but more fights later on. All they need is George Plimpton. Will have Hemingway's 60th birthday party. All will go to Valencia. There never was such a summer in prospect. All expenses charge to firm and new stuff for Death in the Afternoon. All Antonio wants, except to be the greatest matador that ever lived, is to be with them. Just back from his bull ranch. 6250-f
  - Papa Mary [Ernest and Mary Hemingway] to Ed[ward] Hotchner, 1959 June 18, D, 1 item. (Box-folder 3:82)
    Telegram. See Hotchner in Suecia the 27th. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 June 19, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:83)
    Two things he can bring: shooting jacket and boat pants. Weather wonderful. Thinks Hotchner can find place he has always been looking for. Terrific ones like on the Riviera before they ruined it. Wonderful to be seeing him soon. 6250-f
  - Mr. Papa [Ernest Hemingway] to "Bron" [Bronislaw Zielinski], 1959 June 24, ALS, 5 pp. on 4 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:84)
    Thanks for letters. Hemingway could not find African pictures for him. Nor could he answer his very intelligent questions. Should have two secretaries. Seen 14 bull fights since they got to Spain. Antonio [Ordez] was badly gored on May 30th. Enjoyed magazine and will try to be a good Polish writer. Discusses the things wrongly accredited to him in June 20th edition of Paris Match: "Some of it was interesting. But it was all shit and I did not say it." Discusses how, for some strange reason, "probably because Mary is so lovely," that they are very well liked." Hemingway loves Spain the way he loves Idaho. Talks about the story, The Cross Roads. 6250-g
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Bron" [Bronislaw Zielinski], 1959 August 9, LS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:85)
    Mislaid Zielinski's letter about the details of the check for the prize. Cannot locate it. Maybe blown off terrace where he writes or confused with Mary's mail. Could he repeat instructions? Worried that Hemingway's letters to Zielinski may be censored in Poland. Send a cable once he gets this letter. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-g
  - Mr. Papa [Ernest Hemingway] to "Bron" [Bronislaw Zielinski], 1959 August 29, LS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:86)
    Thanks for letter of August 18. Just sent him check for $1000. Let Hemingway know when he gets it. Answers a number of questions about [The Green Hills of Africa]. Plans to return to Idaho for fall and winter. Congratulates Zielinski for his election to the Supreme Council. Hemingway won't be in Spain until June. Discusses problems with translations. Wishes he could read Kolzov's Spanish Diary. Zielinski is a true and good friend and appreciated the cable about the crash: "There was no-one hurt and that is all that matters in crashes."Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-g
  - Hemingstene [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 September 14, LS, 4 pp. on 4 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:87)
    Back in Madrid after swing around circuit. They finally put Antonio [Ordez] in jail after "packing up his picadors." He loses ten fights and 5,000,000 pesetas. His training has been really fractured. Two more fights and he goes to Peru. How do the business deals go? Relates of his trip through Spain. Got pick-pocketed signing autographs. Anotonio's suspension is for one month. Mary will go to New York October 5th and Hemingway to Havana on the 18th. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch-muru" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 September 16, LS. 7 pp. on 7 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:88)
    Tells of great photographs to be sent to Hotchner and of his experiences. Disaster when Antonio [Ordez] was put into the "can" on picador deal. Nobody stuck with Antonio; picadors used after they had been suspended under other names. He misses ten fights. Mary feeling fine again. Hemingway's brother wanted permission to print his letters, with mother a bitch and father a suicide. Hemingway against using letters of living. Damned if brother dredges up all the trouble Hemingway has been in just to make money. Butter to buy himself, but no Hemingway ever paid blackmail. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Boxman" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 September 20, LS, 4 pp. on 4 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:89)
    Regarding cars in Key West. Will need Buick fixed for drive to Idaho. Will sail Liberté October 27 and arriving in New York November 2. Flying down to Finca, then to Key West. Going to see Antonio [Ordez]'s finish season at Nimes, and shoot stuff for Life magazine. Then he will drive to Paris to see Mary off. Building log cabins in Ketchum, [Idaho]. Anxious to get bull stuff wrapped up so he can go back to finish his novel and rest awhile. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 October [2], LS, 6 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:90)
    Thanks Hotchner for handling station-wagon deal. Discusses race at Langhey. Seeing Mary off tomorrow. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-f
  - Ernesto to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 November 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:91)
    Good flight. Mary friendly but holds to same program. Will go to Ketchum to help with Antonio [Ordez] and Carmen on certain conditions: no cooking, and he is not to shoot with Mrs. Gray unless Mary is present. Mary will go to New York to write. Hemingway moves as cheerfully as possible like in a Kafka nightmare. He is bone-tired and very beat up emotionally. Wants to get back to writing. One of the big issues is that he expects others to subordinate themselves to his writing, and thus make them lead lives of drudges. Will tell about the real revolution in Cuba. Hopes United States won't cut sugar quota. He will be amazed at change. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1959 December 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:92)
    Mary sleeps well. Her bones are healing O.K and her cast comes off December 26. Talks about Buick commercials. He thinks them in excellent taste. Will let Finca by January 16th. 6250-f
  - Ernest Hemingway to Life Magazine, [1959 July 7 - 1960 June 2], TMs, 18 pp. on 18 l. (Box-folder 3:93)
    Correspondence regarding The Dangerous Summer. Also includes correspondence from Life magazine to Ernest Hemingway. Life not to publish [Dangerous Summer?] because it will be an appendix to Death in the Afternoon. Life urges him to reconsider; they will mention book. They are publishing Mary's story. Much about rivalry between [Luis Miguel] DominguÍn and [Antonio] Ordez. Hemingway refuses to interrupt present research to do special piece. Much about dickering regarding price, size, etc. Hemingway says hard economics, not vanity, dictates figures. Write regarding Antonio and photographs with Bill Lang. Sent advance payment of $10,000 for bull-fighting article. Discusses Mary's shattered elbow. Life hopes to print article in single issue. Hemingway defends why piece is so long (63,562 words). There are no deaths, so had to build characters, feelings, etc. Can call whole thing off if hard to fit in during election year. Would have been easier if Miguel or Antonio had been killed. Mary pretty well destroyed, but it functioning. Finished at 108,746 words. Will get to work on Scribner book for 1961. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1960 January 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:94)
    Thanks him for tending to business. Getting off tonight. Just signed papers for banking for corporation. Talks about his signature. Thanks for fine pictures. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Pecas" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1960 February 8, LS, 3 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:95)
    Thanks Hotchner for clippings, etc. Glad show went well. Alfred [Rice] appropriately gloomy. Finished 8,000 words in second part of the piece. Goes good, but it will be better when he can get out in boat and get rid of staleness. Not thinking of Dan's book. No plan for serialization, but Life would have first call since George Plimpton mentioned it to them first. They would be glad to give advance. They did publish The Old Man and the Sea. Mary's arm coming along well with massage and therapy. She is optimistic. Hemingway lives in a sort of vacuum of work. Val is organizing everything properly. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-f
  - Dr. Hemingstein [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1960 February 18, LS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:96)
    Thanks for words on project. Would like to know status of various things. [Evi] Sevaroid comes to lunch and steals you blind, always winning as a man of impeachable ethics. Alfred [Rice] sent some cuttings. Have 17,000 words done on piece since the 25th. Mary's arm is good. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-f
  - Mister Papa [Ernest Hemingway] to "Bron" [Bronislaw Zielinski], 1960 February 20, LS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:97)
    Just a note that he received Zielinski's second letter and that Mary's arm is doing better and that he is working very hard. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-g
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Hotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1960 March 12, LS, 4 pp. on 4 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:98)
    [Gary Cooper] called, enthusiastic regarding After the Storm, but spooked about pictures, due to strike. Thinks it OK to take advance payment on it. Discusses future of screen play. Cooper really wants to go into television. Sorry Hotchner is having trouble with censorship on the "K film" [The Snows of Kilimanjaro]. Hemingway wrote it as morally as he could. No fish in gulf, but good cock fighting, swimming, etc. No faith in play unless big sum of money changes hands. All of those bastards have money instead of blood in their veins. Best to think money is counterfeited until it is banked. Letter in the hand of Hemingway's secretary. 6250-f
  - "Papa" [Ernest Hemingway] to "Dotch" [Aaron Edward Hotchner], 1960 March 31, LS, 4 pp. on 4 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 3:99)